Finding Aid for Anson DePuy Van Buren papers, 1846-1885
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Anson DePuy Van Buren papers 1846-1885
Van Buren, Anson De Puy.
2 linear feet
86255 Aa 2
Western Michigan teacher, businessman and local historian. Correspondence, journal, speeches, notes and articles.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The provenance of this collection is uncertain.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Anson De Peuy Van Buren was born April 22, 1822, at Kinderhook, Columbia County, NY. In 1826, his family moved to New York Mills, Oneida County, NY. It was there that Van Buren received his first education in the village schools. In 1836, his family moved to Battle Creek, Michigan. Largely self-taught and without a formal education, Van Buren was able at age sixteen to receive a certificate to teach at the Goguac Prairie School. He continued to teach there until the spring of 1843, when he entered the Michigan University at Kalamazoo. In the summer of 1846, he entered the University at Ann Arbor, attending until 1849. Thereafter, he taught at various places until the fall of 1857, when he moved to Mississippi due to health reasons. There he was in charge of an academy near Yazoo City. A year later, Van Buren moved back to Battle Creek to open a select school, and finished his successful career as teacher at the Climax high school.
In 1859, Van Buren published his book entitled, "Jottings of a Year's Sojourn in the South", and in 1864, he began his career in life insurance which he continued until his death. In 1866, he married Miss Mary L. Gibson. They resided in Galesburg, where he held various town offices. He died June 27, 1892.
The collection is arranged into four series: Correspondence; Journals; Speeches, notes and articles; and Other materials. The collection documents his career as a teacher in Battle Creek, Kalamazoo and Galesburg, Michigan. Of interest are his experiences as a teacher in Mississippi before the Civil War. The correspondence and journals reveal his scholarly and political interests. The collection also includes minutes, 1861-1876, of the Galesburg Temperance Society.
Subjects:
Battle Creek (Mich.); Education--Michigan.; Galesburg (Mich.); Galesburg Temperance Society (Mich.); Kalamazoo (Mich.); Kalamazoo County (Mich.); Michigan--Social life and customs--1841-1850.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; Mississippi.; Schools--Mississippi.; Schools--Michigan.; Southern states.; Teachers--Mississippi.; Teachers--Michigan.; Temperance--Michigan--Galesburg.; Education--Mississippi.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Correspondence
  - 1846-1850 (Box 1)
  - 1851-1855 (Box 1)
  - 1856-1858 (Box 1)
  - 1859-1860 (Box 1)
  - 1861-1865 (Box 1)
  - 1866 (Box 1)
  - 1867-1875 (Box 1)
  - 1876-1885 (Box 1)
- Journals
  - February-March 1855 (Box 1)
  - April 1855-June 1856 (Box 1)
  - June-September 1856 (Box 1)
  - September-1856-January 1857 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1857 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1857 (Box 1)
  - June-August 1857 (Box 1)
  - August-November 1857 (Box 1)
  - January 1859-January 1860 (Box 1)
  - February-December 1860 (Box 1)
  - January 1861-January 1862 (Box 1)
  - 1862-1866 [fragmentary] (Box 1)
- Speeches, notes and articles
  - Various topics, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Various topics, 10 folders (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Scrapbook containing obituaries and Kalamazoo historical items (Box 2)
  - Minutes of the Galesburg Temperance Society, 1861-1876 (Box 2)
  - Teachers register, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Poetry and essay book (Box 2)
  - School book with personal correspondence, 1854-1857 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks and printed items (Box 2)